## Alberto Stefanelli

### RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests include voting behaviour, democratic representation, and methodology. I am currently working on radical belief systems, liberal values, and polarisation. Methods wise, I am interested in matching and standardisation techniques, graphical causal model and DAGs, Conjoint Experiments, Structural Equation Modelling, quantitative text analysis and data visualisation.

Centre for Sociological Research
KU Leuven
Parkstraat 45
Leuven, Belgium

**☎** | Mobile: +39 340 6360909 (IT)

http://www.albertostefanelli.com

alberto.stefanelli.main@gmail.com alberto.stefanelli@kuleuven.be

## **EDUCATION**

2018 – 2022 **Doctoral Education** 

PHD CANDIDATE AT CENTRE FOR SOCIOLOGICAL RESEARCH Faculty of Social Sciences<sup>1</sup>, KU Leuven, Belgium.

Sponsor: Prof. dr. Bart Meuleman

2018 – 2020 **Master Degree** 

MASTER OF STATISTICS Faculty of Science<sup>2</sup>, KU Leuven, Belgium

2016 - 2018 **Master Degree** 

MASTER OF ARTS (MA), POLITICAL SCIENCE Central European University<sup>3</sup>, Budapest, Hungary Thesis Supervisor: Gabor Toka

Cumulative GPA: 3.83/4 Rank/Class Size: 1/10 **2012 - 2015 Bachelor Degree** 

1ST GRADE DEGREE IN POLITICAL SCIENCE, INTERNATIONAL STUDIES, PUBLIC ADMINISTRATION University of Padua, Italy Avg. Grade: 28.53/30. Final Mark: 110/110. Magna cum laude

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>3</sup>According to QS Ranking, the Leuven Statistics Research Centre (LStat) is among top 10 program in Europe for Mathematical and Statistical Sciences and top 50 in the world.

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>3</sup>According to QS Ranking, the Faculty of Social Sciences is among top 20 departments in Europe for Social, Political and Behavioural Sciences and top 50 in the world.

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>3</sup>Central European University (CEU) is a graduate-level, English-language university accredited in the U.S. In 2015, CEU ranked among top 30 Universities in Europe for Political Science.

#### 2018 - Present

### External consultant and analyst

ZK ANALYTICS, OXFORD CENTRE FOR INNOVATION, UK Analysis and report for:

- 1. **World Organization of the Scout Movement** Measuring the impact of Scout activities on personal development. Multi country analysis using propensity score matching and multilevel regression analyses.
- 2. **Ministry of Transportation of United Kingdom** Capability, health and mobility of older People. Complex survey design and panel data analysis with fixed effect and conditional probit estimators.
- 3. **in2Science** Analysis of experimental and semiexperimental data in a multilevel panel data design to assess the impact of specific educational programs on disadvantage children' academic performances.

#### 2018 - PRESENT

#### Consultant and analyst for the ECPR

EUROPEAN CONSORTIUM FOR POLITICAL RESEARCH (ECPR) Analysis and improvement of the questionnaires for the ECPR Methods Schools.

### 06/2018 - 09/2018

## Research Assistant for the Intellectual Theme Initiative

CENTRAL EUROPEAN UNIVERSITY

Data analysis, text mining and web scraping for the project Text Analysis Across Disciplines

### 2015 - 2017

**Social Media Manager and Communication Specialist**Social media manager of various academic and nonacademic projects (i.e. Il Voto Sotto Esame, Politica e Storia SISP Standing Group, Team Populism)

#### 2015 - 2017 **Project leader**

RESEARCH CENTRE "CENTRO GIORGIO LAGO", UNIVERSITY OF PADUA, ITALY

In-depth analysis of the regional (2015) and mayoral (2016) elections of Veneto and Friuli (Italy). Project in partnership with Corriere del Veneto (RCS).

### 2015 - 2017 Research assistant for SKY TG

YouTrend/Quorum for Sky TG, Turin, Italy Data scraping for the 2016 Italian mayoral elections night, exit polls, real-time forecasts, visualisation of voting patterns using QGIS.

#### 2012 Campaign strategist and communication manager

ASSOCIAZIONE PER ANNAMARIA DAMIANO SINDACO, DESENZANO DEL GARDA, ITALY

Chief of the communication and strategy team for the electoral campaign of the mayoral candidate Annamaria Damiano.

### **PUBLICATIONS**

## PUBLISHED PAPERS

- [1] A. Stefanelli and M. Almagisti, "Costi della politica e finanziamenti: Il livello locale", in *Il Finanziamento Alla Politica in Italia*, ser. Biblioteca Di Testi e Studi (1189), D. R. Piccio, Ed., Carocci, 2018, ISBN: 978-88-430-8676-4.
- [2] A. Stefanelli, "The Electoral Consolidation of the Five Star Movement", *Quaderni di Scienza Politica*, vol. Il Movimento Cinque Stelle: Prospettive di Ricerca a Confronto, no. 3, M. Almagisti and P. R. Graziano, Eds., Dec. 2017, ISSN: 1124-7959.
- [3] M. Almagisti and A. Stefanelli, "Dove soffia il vento del Nord", in *Cambiamento o Assestamento? Le Elezioni Amministrative Del 2016*, Istituto Carlo Cattaneo, 2016, pp. 9–22, ISBN: 978-88-941126-2-7.
- [4] —, "Voto al candidato presidente e liste personali e regionali. Il Veneto in prospettiva comparata", *DEMOCRAZIA E DIRITTO*, no. 3, pp. 44–62, 2015, ISSN: 1972-5590. DOI: 10.3280/DED2015-003003.

### Papers under review

[5] A. Stefanelli, "Populist voters are irrational. Testing spatial models using populist attitudes", Accepted in the special issue The Political Psychology of Populism on the European Journal of Political Research (EJPR). Editiors: Ryan E. Carlin, Kirk A. Hawkins, and Levente Littvay.

## SELECTED CONFERENCE TALKS

- [6] A. Stefanelli, "The Downsian irrationality of Populist Voters. Testing spatial models using populist attitudes", presented at the Politicologenetmaal, Politicologenetmaal Conference, Leiden, 2018.
- [7] —, "Populist voters are irrational. Testing spatial models using populist attitudes", presented at the Team Populism Conference, Team Populism Conference (invited), Budapest, 2017.
- [8] E. K. Jenne, R. Aguilar, Z. Enyedi, A. Stefanelli, and O. Utku, "Populism: Ideology, potential causes, individual and societal factors, and possible consequences.", presented at the CEU Open House 2017: Round-Table Discussion on Populism. (invited), 2017.
- [9] A. Stefanelli, "Competence or Proximity? Insights from a conjoint experiment", presented at the Annual Conference of the Italian Political Science Association, Urbino, 2017.
- [10] —, "Il M5S alle urne: Elezioni nazionali e amministrative a confronto", presented at the Ciclo Di Seminari "Movimento 5 Stelle: Prospettive a Confronto", (invited), University of Padua, Nov. 18, 2016.
- [11] A. Stefanelli and M. Almagisti, "Costi della politica e finanziamenti: Il livello locale", presented at the Finanziamento Ai Partiti Politici in Italia: Fonti Di Finanziamento, Trasparenza, Organizzazione Interna e Controlli Esterni, (invited), University of Turin, May 19–20, 2016.
- [12] —, "Il voto di preferenza nelle principali città al voto", presented at the Post-Electoral Seminar of the Italian Society of Electoral Studies (SISE), 2016.

[13] M. Almagisti, N. Scarnera, and A. Stefanelli, "Tendenze nel voto in Veneto: Voto di preferenza e voto al candidato presidente", presented at the Annual Conference of the Italian Political Science Association (SISP), 2015.

## WORKING PAPERS

- 1. A. Stefanelli "The Rise of Illiberal Populism. Insights from Latin America"
- 2. A. Stefanelli "From Ideological Convergence to Affective Hostility. Resolving the populist polarization paradox"
- 3. A. Stefanelli, F. Rossetti "Conditional Benevolents: Testing welfare conditionality among populist voters"
- 4. A. Stefanelli, M. Lukac "Power Analysis in Conjoint Experiments"
- 5. A. Stefanelli "Standardization techniques. A comparison using Monte Carlo simulations"

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

# MAY 2020 Instructor for "Introduction to Conjoint Experiments" (Invited) (ECPR)

University of Bamberg, Bamberg, Germany Instructor at the Winter School in Methods and Techniques organised by the European Consortium for Political Research (ECPR)

# DECEMBER 2019 Instructor for "Propensity Matching and Standardisation techniques" (Invited)

HEBREW UNIVERSITY OF JERUSALEM, JERUSALEM, ISRAEL Instructor for a workshop at The 15th International Graduate Conference in Political Science, International Relations, and Public Policy (with Sharon Gilad)

# 2018 - 2019 TA for several courses at ECPR School in Advanced Methods

CENTRAL EUROPEAN UNIVERSITY AND BAMBER UNIVERSITY Teaching Assistant for:

- 1. **Automated Collection of Web and Social Data** Instructor: Theresa Gessler (2019) and Pablo Barbera (2018).
- 2. Logistic Regression and Generalised Linear Models Instructor: Michał Kotnarowski
- 3. R Basics Instructor: Akos Mate
- 4. **TA for Regression Refresher** Instructor: Littvay (Levi) Levente

### 2017 - 2018 TA for Text Mining Boot Camp

CENTRAL EUROPEAN UNIVERSITY, BUDAPEST, HUNGARY Teaching Assistant in the Text Mining and Text analysis Boot Camp. Introduction to Text Mining with R. Instructor: Jessie Labov and Littvay (Levi) Levente

### WINTER 2018 TA for Experimental Political Science

CENTRAL EUROPEAN UNIVERSITY, BUDAPEST, HUNGARY Teaching Assistant and guest speaker (Human Intelligence Task platforms) in the Experimental Political Science course. Instructor: Littvay (Levi) Levente

## ACADEMIC HONOURS AND GRANTS

#### 2019 Celso Ghini Award for the best MA thesis

ITALIAN ELECTORAL STUDIES ASSOCIATION, ROME

## 2016 - 2018 Advanced certificate in Research Methodology and Social Analysis

CENTRAL EUROPEAN UNIVERSITY, BUDAPEST, HUNGARY

#### 2018 Research Grant

CENTRAL EUROPEAN UNIVERSITY, BUDAPEST, HUNGARY Research grant for a survey experiment.

### 2016 - 2018 Master's Scholarship recipient

CENTRAL EUROPEAN UNIVERSITY, BUDAPEST, HUNGARY Full tuition fee and health insurance.

### 2015 Academic honour for thesis and grade excellence

University of Padua, Italy

Thesis title: Personalisation and Presidentialisation of Politics in the Italian Regional Elections.

### OTHER RESEARCH AND ACADEMIC EXPERIENCES

# 2018 - PRESENT Principal Investigator for several Work Packages in the National Belgian Electoral Study and National Belgian Minor-

**ity Study** KU Leuven, Leuven, Belgium

The BBe van, BBe van, BBBeren

## 2018 - PRESENT Member of the Experiments and Survey teams of Team Populism<sup>4</sup>.

TEAM LEADER: RYAN CARLIN

# 2017 – 2018 Vice president of the Central European University Populism Research Group (POPRES)

CENTRAL EUROPEAN UNIVERSITY, BUDAPEST, HUNGARY

### OTHER EXPERIENCES

### 2013 – 2014 Member of Statute Commission of the Italian Democratic Party

PARTITO DEMOCRATICO, MILANO, ITALY

Review of national and Lombardy regional statute of the Italian Democratic Party (PD) according to the suggestions of regional and national elective assemblies

#### Language skills

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>4</sup>Team Populism brings together renowned scholars from Europe and the Americas to study the causes and consequences of populism.

ITALIAN Native speaker

ENGLISH Oral: Proficient (C2) – Written: Proficient (C2)

FRENCH Oral: Basic (A2) – Written: Independent (B1)

## SOFTWARE AND PROGRAMMING SKILLS

PROFICIENCY LEVEL Linux, Mac OS, Windows

R, Mplus, 上下X, Shiny, R Makdown, QGIS, SPSS

**GIMP** 

INTERMEDIATE Phyton, HTML, CSS

BASIC LEVEL MySQL, STATA, PHP, Java